<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://dcjmp90.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://dcjmp90.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-01-02T21:45:43-06:00</updated><id>https://dcjmp90.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">build-essentials</title><subtitle>A blog of tech and randomness.</subtitle><author><name>Jon Perry</name></author><entry><title type="html">What is a Machine Learning Engineer?</title><link href="https://dcjmp90.github.io/blog/2022/01/02/what-is-a-machine-learning-engineer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is a Machine Learning Engineer?" /><published>2022-01-02T15:25:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-01-02T15:25:00-06:00</updated><id>https://dcjmp90.github.io/blog/2022/01/02/what-is-a-machine-learning-engineer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dcjmp90.github.io/blog/2022/01/02/what-is-a-machine-learning-engineer.html">&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt in anyone's mind that the technology industry has been moving faster than ever. No one has anticipated the growth that there is now. If you find someone that says otherwise, please ask them if we can borrow their crystal ball. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the midst of all these technological advances, new job opportunities and new industry needs arise. I think we have all been gradually getting comfortable with the buzzwords: Data Science, Big Data, Cloud whatever. You might be seeing another job starting to circulate more and more through each hiring iteration and joining the ranks of top careers of our time: Machine Learning Engineer (MLE). What in the world is that? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;https://i.ibb.co/RN3hb8r/Screen-Shot-2021-12-03-at-3-09-32-PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;Machine Learning Engineer Jokes&quot;&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;My current role's slack channel snippet. Love it.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Your Background.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probably a highly debatable topic. Your most common discipline you will see cropping up time and time again will be Computer Science. It is my discipline, and I would say that it sets you up for success in this field. However, this isn’t the only path one can take to achieve a successful career as an MLE. No fancy buzzwords or specific tools. I will not be imploring you to learn  ____ programming language. Those will change over time; they always do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;https://i.ibb.co/93d7Xcm/wordcloud-cropped.png&quot; alt=&quot;Machine Learning Engineer Backgrounds&quot;&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;These are all the types of Master's degrees held by MLE's in my lab.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Realistically, you will need some type of established background with Software Engineering and Machine Learning to be suitable for this job. I think there are a ton of ways to obtain those skills, and my current lab easily shows that. I think this is actually a strength that our lab has. Diversity is never a bad thing – true for all but specifically talking about academic background diversity. Machine Learning is a multi-faceted problem and anyone can bring value in that regard. But you better know some ML and have some coding abilities! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to know the skill set and competencies that allows me to produce and deliver. While I may cover some of that in the next section, I will mention upfront that this isn’t a role where you will be tasked with clear objectives all the time. It isn’t something that always has answers or well-defined procedures for every scope of problem. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;What Do You Do?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;align-items: center; align-content: center; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;https://c.tenor.com/96yg4s4p2MMAAAAC/pain-knights-tale.gif&quot; alt=&quot;A knight's Tale gif&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Mostly kidding...mostly.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I Google searched this question myself “What an MLE Does” as I was writing this. It’s not that I don’t know what I do, but this is actually a lot harder to put into general terms that everyone can understand. There is a TON of misinformation about this field, and a lot of people giving advice that are not MLE’s or they are simply translating job postings from recruiters that are also not in this field. I will do my best to be transparent, but I do want to keep things abstract. I will have other posts on specifics regarding my previous roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy. You build cool things. Next question! There’s actually more merit in that statement than I would like there to be. We research problems, and sometimes we find ways to repurpose, reengineer, or translate a solution from something else to ours, however it is on a more frequent basis where we find ourselves on the tip of the spear developing novel solutions. This is where some people may disagree with me. To those readers, what I am saying is true, but there are other roles that may be primary and MLE’s are secondary on this at your company. It really depends where in the company you are working. If you want more exposure to this portion, then I suggest you work in a labs division or research and development branch of the company. Other branches and divisions will probably be provided with a solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;...So..What Do You Do...&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;align-items: center; align-content: center; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;https://thumbs.gfycat.com/EminentTinyAlbino-size_restricted.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Who is your daddy gif&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solutions we are developing are typically Machine Learning algorithms that will be deployed into an application or infrastructure that will be served to users. Users will typically indirectly interact with these ML algorithms you developed through this workflow, usually called an ML pipeline, which is something you and some software engineers with other specializations will create. These ML pipelines will be automated and that means there will be zero direct human assistance or intervention within that user's interaction with your live product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of your smartphone. It probably has a voice assistant currently supported on it, right?  
    Well, I can tell you there are quite a few Machine Learning Engineers that worked on that virtual assistant. At the very beginning, that assistant needs to take your voice and translate it to text before it can understand what you are saying. This alone is an ML model that will require an ML pipeline. There will be a team of MLE’s for this. They had to develop that ML solution and build the workflow to capture your voice and feed a formatted input into their ML algorithm. We obviously know the desired output will be exactly what you said in text format, and this would be fed to the next ML model to the next and to the next and so on. You may not have realized this, but there are probably 10’s to 100’s of Machine Learning models that make up the pipeline for your voice to intelligent response(s) being displayed or said back to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is a Machine Learning Engineer? We are Software Engineers with a strong background and specialization into Machine Learning. We are the meat and potatoes of that virtual assistant or any other intelligent system. To list some off the top of my head: virtual assistants, streaming services, self-driving cars, face recognition, bank fraud detection, better graphics from your game, airport security, agriculture, food service, cleaning services, and even detection of Alzheimer's disease. Machine Learning Engineers play a key role in every one of these areas. You can safely assume that every single industry will have MLE’s at work. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jon Perry</name></author><summary type="html">There is no doubt in anyone's mind that the technology industry has been moving faster than ever. No one has anticipated the growth that there is now. If you find someone that says otherwise, please ask them if we can borrow their crystal ball.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A dream does not become reality through thought alone; It takes resilience, determination, and planning.</title><link href="https://dcjmp90.github.io/blog/2021/11/29/a-dream-of-computer-science.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A dream does not become reality through thought alone; It takes resilience, determination, and planning." /><published>2021-11-29T10:45:13-06:00</published><updated>2021-11-29T10:45:13-06:00</updated><id>https://dcjmp90.github.io/blog/2021/11/29/a-dream-of-computer-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dcjmp90.github.io/blog/2021/11/29/a-dream-of-computer-science.html">&lt;p&gt;Life altering decisions are never easy, nor will those changes happen within the most optimal timeline for you. Of course you want the change, who wouldn’t want better? It sounds amazing in theory, but the reality of it is a tough pill to swallow. This is my journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a high school student with very little direction, I didn’t contribute much to my early years of education and career. I worked at Dairy Queen, played hacky sack at lunch, and ditched classes after lunch for fast-food and video games. Needless to say, Yale wasn’t going to be knocking on my door. At that time, I was struggling to maintain a 2.0 grade point average, which included a failing grade in your run-of-the-mill high school algebra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there will be little shock and awe to my next step in life: The United States Air Force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;The Spark that Lit the Flame&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether we see it or not, we all come to a fork in the road countless times throughout life. At some point I found myself armed to the teeth at some munitions depot in the middle of South Korea for a 12 hour night shift. I was alone all night with my thoughts. What am I doing with my life...How did I get here...Is this it? Many questions and thoughts began to overwhelm me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;At some point, everything's gonna go south on you and you're going to say, this is it. This is how I end. Now you can either accept that, or you can get to work&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t know what I was going to do, but I knew I wanted to do something more with my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, I gravitated towards computers and tech from all my time building computers and playing video games. Computer Science was the most common theme from a ton of Google searching. I need to figure out this math thing if I want to succeed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;This is Where the Fun Begins…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enrolled into college at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.utsa.edu/&quot;&gt;University of Texas at San Antonio&lt;/a&gt;...randomly. I had no reason for this specific school, but it was as good of a place as any in my opinion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working and full-time college would be a death sentence. I figured out that I could live on some grant funds as well as my military benefits if I had roommates in student housing, but I would need to get rid of nearly all of my possessions. I am now living with a gym bag, suitcase worth of clothes, a really good laptop, and no transportation of any kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 4 remedial math courses, I finally got through college algebra and started my path towards Calculus! Now I can get to my actual degree. The only problem is that I’m on a real time clock here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And my benefits are not a specific amount, rather a specific time allotment. It is very strange when you take it out of context, but that means they cover X amount of time no matter the cost per semester. I decided to take 5 courses each semester to get the most value from my benefits without failing my courses. I was in and committed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I eventually navigated my first &lt;a href=&quot;https://catalog.utsa.edu/search/?P=CS%201083&quot;&gt;Programming 1&lt;/a&gt; course, which gave me the programming bug...I was reinvigorated and hungry for more! Each course got harder and harder to the point I spent every day of my Spring breaks and weekends in the computer lab working. This isn’t the mindset or the necessary devotion one requires to successfully complete this degree, but I think it’s needed if you wish to truly learn the ins and outs of the topics covered. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Is CS Hard? Yes and No&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not and will never say that Computer Science majors are “elite” or some other bogus claim. Yes, we do have our “elitist” just like any other major, but that really says more about the individual and less about the major. These courses and how they must be taught are really different from your traditional college course. After my civics and other general courses, I never saw things like McGraw Hill, textbooks, or even scantrons for the remainder of my degree. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real strangeness to this degree will be that the tests will still be conducted with paper and pencil, while the entirety of the course outside of tests is all computers and coding within an integrated development environment (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Integrated_development_environment&quot;&gt;IDE&lt;/a&gt;). That’s a huge disconnect for me, but it’s a perfect preparation for interviewing as a Software Engineer. Let’s not open that can of worms just yet. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each course I had roughly one programming assignment due every week, which is multiplied by how many courses I’m taking, and I am also learning the language or principles being taught. Too much? Don't worry, there's more! There will be a midterm, final exam, personal/group project, and potential for quizzes on top for each and every class. To give you an idea of complexity, we had a first programming assignment assigning some data into a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linked_list&quot;&gt;linked list&lt;/a&gt; in early course levels, and we would have to create our own &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garbage_collection_(computer_science)&quot;&gt;garbage collector&lt;/a&gt; in C for a first assignment in later courses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this program will become hard if you don’t continually try to develop your skills and understanding by diving deeper into the coursework. I unintentionally took this route and it paid dividends. It’s important, in my opinion, to ask the why about anything you’re doing. I would also attribute my continued growth to the types of people I surrounded myself with. I chose to study with the best of the best in my degree program. Not to be lazy and have them take up the slack, but to push each other further and find new limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;The Semester that Would Change Everything&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Junior year of Computer Science started Fall 2018 with a seriously overwhelming amount of programming courses: &lt;a href=&quot;https://catalog.utsa.edu/search/?P=CS%203753&quot;&gt;Data Science&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://catalog.utsa.edu/search/?P=CS%203443&quot;&gt;Application Programming&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://catalog.utsa.edu/search/?P=CS%203424&quot;&gt;Systems Programming&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://catalog.utsa.edu/search/?P=CS%203343&quot;&gt;Analysis of Algorithms&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://catalog.utsa.edu/search/?P=CS%203873&quot;&gt;Computer Networks&lt;/a&gt;. Now you might be able to see where all those assignments will start demoralizing you. The programming languages I was using and/or learning during this semester: Python, Perl, Java, C, AWK, and Bash. Yes, it’s as bad as it sounds. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this grueling semester leads me towards my introduction into &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artificial_intelligence&quot;&gt;Artificial Intelligence&lt;/a&gt;. My Application Programming Professor, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cs.utsa.edu/people/faculty/fernandez-amanda-141&quot;&gt;Dr. Amanda Fernandez&lt;/a&gt;, left me curious about her field of research. It was day 1 of the course, and she gave a brief bio about herself and her research. More specifically, she was touching on her &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_vision&quot;&gt;Computer Vision&lt;/a&gt; research. Man, that is (and still is) the coolest topic to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This curiosity led me to several office hour visits to ask about research and the field she was in. I couldn’t get enough. She would probably say otherwise (joking). It seemed so advanced and unattainable, but I wanted to learn more and get into it. I started with Independent Study and Artificial Intelligence courses taught by Dr. Amanda Fernandez. I started with Natural Language Processing (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_language_processing&quot;&gt;NLP&lt;/a&gt;) and doing some things like sentiment analysis and building chatbots. To be honest, I had no idea what I was doing, but I was learning small pieces of a larger pie while I fell in the right direction. That’s basically our everyday life right? Controlled falls in the right direction. I didn’t fully grasp everything I was doing until I took an advanced topics course of hers called &lt;a href=&quot;https://catalog.utsa.edu/search/?P=CS%204263&quot;&gt;Deep Learning&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first true taste of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_vision&quot;&gt;Computer Vision&lt;/a&gt; was in this &lt;a href=&quot;https://catalog.utsa.edu/search/?P=CS%204263&quot;&gt;Deep Learning&lt;/a&gt; course, and it was actually impressive how powerful it could be. My project in that course was a generative adversarial network (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generative_adversarial_network&quot;&gt;GAN&lt;/a&gt;) that would produce altered images of a provided profile picture. Change their hair, eyes, mouth, etc. This was one of my final and favorite courses I completed in my undergraduate degree. If you ever read this &lt;a href=&quot;https://cs.utsa.edu/people/faculty/clark-larry-140&quot;&gt;Professor Clark&lt;/a&gt;, your course is also one of my favorites! &lt;a href=&quot;https://catalog.utsa.edu/search/?P=CS%202124&quot;&gt;Data Structures&lt;/a&gt; with you is a course I will never forget. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Failed Startup == Personal Growth?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I graduated. One of my colleagues at the time offered me a referral to a start-up company, which I thought was doing me a favor. I took the job to start as a Machine Learning Engineer. This startup had no leadership or engineering to support any type of Machine Learning platform. I was duped. My “friend” left that company shortly after I joined. Fast forward 6 months, I left that company. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this time I still kept in contact with Dr. Fernandez, and I reached out to her about my new status of unemployed. We discussed the alternative of graduate school. I had no idea what to research or do in graduate school, but I knew I wanted to keep pursuing Artificial Intelligence. We found a &lt;a href=&quot;https://research.fb.com/programs/openeds-challenge/&quot;&gt;workshop by Facebook&lt;/a&gt; on a Computer Vision problem I can work on. I ended up publishing 3 months later and flying to South Korea to present my research in an oral presentation at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://openaccess.thecvf.com/content_ICCVW_2019/papers/OpenEDS/Perry_MinENet_A_Dilated_CNN_for_Semantic_Segmentation_of_Eye_Features_ICCVW_2019_paper.pdf&quot;&gt;International Conference on Computer Vision&lt;/a&gt;. Looks like I found my research topic!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Pick It Up &amp; Run With It!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This passion for Computer Vision and the problem space of Semantic Segmentation led me through graduate school. I published once more at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://openeyes-workshop.github.io/downloads/openeyes2020_jonathan_perry_eyeseg_fast_and_efficient_few_shot_semantic_segmentation.pdf&quot;&gt;European Conference on Computer Vision&lt;/a&gt; and I successfully defended my Master Thesis on this research topic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;https://i.ibb.co/bzksjjy/img-20191111-161950.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MinENet Oral Presentation&quot;&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Oral Presentation at an AI Summit shortly after my return from ICCV2019 in South Korea.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Fernandez’s research lab, Vision and Aritificial Intelligence Laboratory (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.utsa.edu/~fernandez/vail.html&quot;&gt;VAIL&lt;/a&gt;), acted as an incubator for me in many ways. Letting passion drive my learning and growth was the best decision I have ever made. I wouldn’t know where I would be today without my friendships and mentorships developed through research at VAIL. If any of you VAIL members read this, I miss you all and I truly want to thank you for everything!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all led me to now. I am working my dream job as a Machine Learning Engineer and I AM LOVING IT! &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jon Perry</name></author><summary type="html">Life altering decisions are never easy, nor will those changes happen within the most optimal timeline for you. Of course you want the change, who wouldn’t want better? It sounds amazing in theory, but the reality of it is a tough pill to swallow. This is my journey.</summary></entry></feed>