<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://dcjmp90.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://dcjmp90.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-12-07T16:36:39-06:00</updated><id>https://dcjmp90.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">build-essentials</title><subtitle>A blog of tech and randomness.</subtitle><author><name>Jon Perry</name></author><entry><title type="html">What is a Machine Learning Engineer?</title><link href="https://dcjmp90.github.io/blog/2021/12/03/what-is-a-machine-learning-engineer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is a Machine Learning Engineer?" /><published>2021-12-03T15:25:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-12-03T15:25:00-06:00</updated><id>https://dcjmp90.github.io/blog/2021/12/03/what-is-a-machine-learning-engineer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dcjmp90.github.io/blog/2021/12/03/what-is-a-machine-learning-engineer.html">&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt in anyone's mind that the technology industry has been moving faster than ever. No one has anticipated the growth that there is now. If you find someone that says otherwise, please ask them if we can borrow their crystal ball. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the midst of all these technological advances, new job opportunities and new industry needs arise. I think we have all been gradually getting comfortable with the buzzwords: Data Science, Big Data, Cloud whatever. You might be seeing another job starting to circulate more and more through each hiring iteration and joining the ranks of top careers of our time: Machine Learning Engineer (MLE). What in the world is that? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;https://i.ibb.co/RN3hb8r/Screen-Shot-2021-12-03-at-3-09-32-PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;Machine Learning Engineer Jokes&quot;&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;My current role's slack channel snippet. Love it.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Your Background.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probably a highly debatable topic. Your most common discipline you will see cropping up time and time again will be Computer Science. It is my discipline, and I would say that it sets you up for success in this field. However, this isn’t the only path one can take to achieve a successful career as an MLE. No fancy buzzwords or specific tools. I will not be imploring you to learn  ____ programming language. Those will change over time; they always do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;https://i.ibb.co/93d7Xcm/wordcloud-cropped.png&quot; alt=&quot;Machine Learning Engineer Backgrounds&quot;&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;These are all the types of Master's degrees held by MLE's in my lab.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Realistically, you will need some type of established background with Software Engineering and Machine Learning to be suitable for this job. I think there are a ton of ways to obtain those skills, and my current lab easily shows that. I think this is actually a strength that our lab has. Diversity is never a bad thing – true for all but specifically talking about academic background diversity. Machine Learning is a multi-faceted problem and anyone can bring value in that regard. But you better know some ML and have some coding abilities! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to know the skill set and competencies that allows me to produce and deliver. While I may cover some of that in the next section, I will mention upfront that this isn’t a role where you will be tasked with clear objectives all the time. It isn’t something that always has answers or well-defined procedures for every scope of problem. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;&quot;A Day in the Life of...&quot;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;align-items: center; align-content: center; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;https://thumbs.gfycat.com/EminentTinyAlbino-size_restricted.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Who is your daddy gif&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I Google searched this question myself “What an MLE Does” as I was writing this. It’s not that I don’t know what I do, but this is actually a lot harder to put into general terms that everyone can understand. There is a TON of misinformation about this field, and a lot of people giving &quot;insights&quot; that are not MLE’s or they are simply translating job postings from recruiters that are also not in this field. To make a more transparent and REAL example, I decided to just take my last 2 quarters of work into sections with a corresponding core competency of what I did and a segment of my real-world work life. &lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;Writing underway!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jon Perry</name></author><summary type="html">There is no doubt in anyone's mind that the technology industry has been moving faster than ever. No one has anticipated the growth that there is now. If you find someone that says otherwise, please ask them if we can borrow their crystal ball.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A dream does not become reality through thought alone; It takes resilience, determination, and planning.</title><link href="https://dcjmp90.github.io/blog/2021/11/29/a-dream-of-computer-science.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A dream does not become reality through thought alone; It takes resilience, determination, and planning." /><published>2021-11-29T10:45:13-06:00</published><updated>2021-11-29T10:45:13-06:00</updated><id>https://dcjmp90.github.io/blog/2021/11/29/a-dream-of-computer-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dcjmp90.github.io/blog/2021/11/29/a-dream-of-computer-science.html">&lt;p&gt;Life altering decisions are never easy, nor will those changes happen within the most optimal timeline for you. Of course you want the change, who wouldn’t want better? It sounds amazing in theory, but the reality of it is a tough pill to swallow. This is my journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a high school student with very little direction, I didn’t contribute much to my early years of education and career. I worked at Dairy Queen, played hacky sack at lunch, and ditched classes after lunch for fast-food and video games. Needless to say, Yale wasn’t going to be knocking on my door. At that time, I was struggling to maintain a 2.0 grade point average, which included a failing grade in your run-of-the-mill high school algebra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there will be little shock and awe to my next step in life: The United States Air Force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;The Spark that Lit the Flame&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether we see it or not, we all come to a fork in the road countless times throughout life. At some point I found myself armed to the teeth at some munitions depot in the middle of South Korea for a 12 hour night shift. I was alone all night with my thoughts. What am I doing with my life...How did I get here...Is this it? Many questions and thoughts began to overwhelm me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;At some point, everything's gonna go south on you and you're going to say, this is it. This is how I end. Now you can either accept that, or you can get to work&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t know what I was going to do, but I knew I wanted to do something more with my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, I gravitated towards computers and tech from all my time building computers and playing video games. Computer Science was the most common theme from a ton of Google searching. I need to figure out this math thing if I want to succeed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;This is Where the Fun Begins…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enrolled into college at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.utsa.edu/&quot;&gt;University of Texas at San Antonio&lt;/a&gt;...randomly. I had no reason for this specific school, but it was as good of a place as any in my opinion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working and full-time college would be a death sentence. I figured out that I could live on some grant funds as well as my military benefits if I had roommates in student housing, but I would need to get rid of nearly all of my possessions. I am now living with a gym bag, suitcase worth of clothes, a really good laptop, and no transportation of any kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 4 remedial math courses, I finally got through college algebra and started my path towards Calculus! 5 courses each semester to get the most value from my benefits. I was in and committed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually I finally took my first Programming I course, which gave me the programming bug...I was reinvigorated and hungry for more! Each course got harder and harder to the point I spent every day of my Spring breaks in the computer lab working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;The Semester that Would Change Everything&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Junior year of Computer Science started Fall 2018 with a seriously overwhelming amount of programming courses: Data Science, Application Programming, Systems Programming, Analysis of Algorithms, and Computer Networks. Yes, it’s as bad as it sounds. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My introduction to Artificial Intelligence started with the introduction of my Application Programming Professor, Dr. Amanda Fernandez, which left me curious about her field of research. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This curiosity led me to several office hour visits to ask about research and the field she was in. I couldn’t get enough. It seemed so advanced and seemingly unattainable, but I wanted to learn more and get into it. I started with Independent Study and Artificial Intelligence courses taught by Dr. Amanda Fernandez.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Failed Startup == Personal Growth?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I graduated. One of my colleagues at the time offered me a referral to a start-up company, which I thought was doing me a favor. I took the job to start as a Machine Learning Engineer. This startup had no leadership or engineering to support any type of Machine Learning platform. I was duped. My “friend” left that company shortly after I joined. Fast forward 6 months, I left that company. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this time I still kept in contact with Dr. Fernandez, and I reached out to her about my new status of unemployed. We discussed the alternative of graduate school. I had no idea what to research or do in graduate school, but I knew I wanted to keep pursuing Artificial Intelligence. We found a &lt;a href=&quot;https://research.fb.com/programs/openeds-challenge/&quot;&gt;workshop by Facebook&lt;/a&gt; on a Computer Vision problem I can work on. I ended up publishing 3 months later and flying to South Korea to present my research in an oral presentation at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://openaccess.thecvf.com/content_ICCVW_2019/papers/OpenEDS/Perry_MinENet_A_Dilated_CNN_for_Semantic_Segmentation_of_Eye_Features_ICCVW_2019_paper.pdf&quot;&gt;International Conference on Computer Vision&lt;/a&gt;. Looks like I found my research topic!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Find Your Passion, Let It Guide You!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This passion for Computer Vision and the problem space of Semantic Segmentation led me through graduate school. I published once more at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://openeyes-workshop.github.io/downloads/openeyes2020_jonathan_perry_eyeseg_fast_and_efficient_few_shot_semantic_segmentation.pdf&quot;&gt;European Conference on Computer Vision&lt;/a&gt; and I successfully defended my Master Thesis on this research topic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;https://i.ibb.co/bzksjjy/img-20191111-161950.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MinENet Oral Presentation&quot;&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Oral Presentation at an AI Summit shortly after my return from ICCV2019 in South Korea.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.utsa.edu/~fernandez/vail.html&quot;&gt;Dr. Fernandez’s research lab&lt;/a&gt; acted as an incubator for me. Letting passion drive my learning and growth was the best decision I have ever made. I am now working my dream job as a Machine Learning Engineer and I AM LOVING IT! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t forget two of the key takeaways I implied here:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Get out of your comfort zone&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;create your network; show your value and worth!&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jon Perry</name></author><summary type="html">Life altering decisions are never easy, nor will those changes happen within the most optimal timeline for you. Of course you want the change, who wouldn’t want better? It sounds amazing in theory, but the reality of it is a tough pill to swallow. This is my journey.</summary></entry></feed>